Greetings everyone. Today I am going to show
you Wan 2.2 trainings. This will be an epic
tutorial. I will cover so many topics, so check
out the video descriptions to learn all. So,
what I am going to show you today? I will show
you how to train Wan 2.2 model to generate
images like these ones. You see, these are
extremely high quality and extremely realistic,
with massive amount of details, textures,
amazing quality, and amazing realism. The
Wan 2.2 is currently the most realistic plus
most advanced model for generating images.
But I will not show only how to train images.
I will show also how to generate videos,
how to train video model, so many things. I
will show how to train on your local computer
with our SECourses Musubi Tuner application.
I have prepared configurations for every GPU,
starting from 6 GB GPUs to 192 GB GPUs. The
configurations are all set. They are separated
into qualities, so you can pick your configuration
according to your GPU and start training right
away and get the most amazing results without
doing all the research that I did for you.
I have literally done over 64 separate
trainings to find out the best workflow,
find out the best parameters, and prepare these
presets. I have used a cloud machine with 8 B200
GPUs to complete these trainings, analyze them.
Moreover, I have developed this Gradio based
application that you will be able to load the
configuration and start training right away.
Furthermore, I will show how to do training on
RunPod. So if you don't have a powerful GPU,
you will be able to train on RunPod. And I will
show how to do training on Massed Compute. Again,
if you don't have a powerful GPU, you will be
able to train on Massed Compute. For example,
you see with this GPU we are able to train with
like 70 minutes with only 2 dollars in 1 hour.
Everything is ready. Some people were asking
me how to train on RunPod and Massed Compute
the Qwen image models. This tutorial
covers the Wan 2.2 training. However,
all of the models that we support in SECourses
Musubi Tuner are exactly same. So you can train
the Qwen image models, Wan models, or the future
models hopefully that will get added like Flux 2,
like Z Image base model, will be
exactly same as in this tutorial.
Moreover, I have updated all of our presets
to the highest quality with lowest amount of
time to generate highest quality images and
videos. So all the image generation and video
generation presets are updated and ready
for you to use. To update these presets,
I have done so many different tests. I have
compared all the results of these tests to
generate videos or images. So many tests have
been made. This tutorial is a product of a massive
research. So many different parameter testing, so
many different workflow testing, and all is ready
for you to use right away with 1 click installers.
So you see from bad videos to good videos.
This tutorial covers text to image
training with only from images,
text to video training with only images or
plus videos, but videos are not necessary,
or image to video training. I have done so many
testing and training only text to video yields the
best results for text to video generation or image
to video generation. The presets are separated,
so if you are not interested in video generation,
you can only use the text to image generation
workflow. Still, it is working on text to video
generation or image to video generation as well.
So all these configs are interchangeable. There
are several tricks. If you want to
generate highest quality images,
you use the text to image configs. If you
want to generate highest quality videos,
you use Wan 2.2 text to video configs. If you want
to generate image to video, still I recommend to
use text to video configs because this is working
better than image to video. It is weird, I know,
but this is my findings. How do I know? Because
I have done so many different testings as you
are seeing. This is a research of a week doing
a lot of comparisons, doing a lot of testing,
experimentation, and all the presets are ready for
you to use right away with the highest quality.
So I will show everything: how to install, how
to set up, how to start training both Windows,
RunPod, Massed Compute. And everything is
literally with 1 click install. Let's begin.
So as usual, I have prepared an amazing post
where you will find everything to follow this
tutorial. However, before starting this tutorial,
you need to watch this main tutorial. So open
this tutorial. This tutorial is our Qwen image
models training tutorial. This is a masterpiece.
This tutorial covers so many different topics
as you are seeing right now. So I recommend
you to watch this tutorial and learn how to use
SECourses Kohya Musubi Tuner premium application.
So I will download the latest zip file. This
zip file includes our latest installers and
configurations. I will move it into my existing
installation folder. Then I will extract the
files here and I will overwrite existing
files. Don't forget that you can also do a
fresh installation. After extraction, double
click Windows install and update.bat file.
This will update the application to the latest
version. Moreover, now we are using uv package
installer along with pip, therefore it is ultra
fast. So you see my update already completed.
Then double click Windows download training
models.bat file. This file will ask you download
which training models. For this tutorial, we need
Wan 2.2 text to video training. If you want to
train Wan 2.2 image to video, then you need to
download it with option 5. Since I already have
downloaded the models, it will just verify their
hash values, and once the verification completed,
we will be ready. This way we are ensuring
that our models are 100 percentage accurately
downloaded, so we will never have any weird bugs,
issues, or problems. If the files were missing,
it would have downloaded them with the maximum
speed with your network connection support.
So now we are ready to begin training. I will
double click Windows start up.bat file. This
will start the latest version of the SECourses
Kohya Musubi Tuner premium application. You see
currently we are at the version 24. This is
where you see the versioning. Then go to Wan
models training. So we are going to use this
tab. Whenever you are going to reload a model,
I recommend to refresh, go to the accurate tab,
and then begin loading. Then click this icon
and go back to your installation folder, enter
inside Wan 2.2 training configs. Now there are
3 configuration folders: Wan 2.2 image to video,
Wan 2.2 text to image, and Wan 2.2 text to video.
So what are the differences between these 3? From
the naming as you can see, Wan 2.2 image to video
trains image to video model. However, there
is only single configuration because if you
want to only generate images, it is not the
model that you need. This model is for only
generating videos. However, I don't recommend to
use this model for training even if you are going
to use image to video models because training
with Wan 2.2 text to video works better than
training with Wan 2.2 image to video, even
for image to video presets. Even for image
to video generation. So for video generation, I
recommend to always use Wan 2.2 text to video,
and for only image generation, I
recommend to use Wan 2.2 text to image.
So let's begin with Wan 2.2 text to image. Now
you will see bunch of configurations like this.
The first numbers are for GPU
VRAM. So if you have 6 GB of GPU,
you need to pick it. If you have 24 GB of GPU,
then you need to pick it. It also shows the
quality. The quality 1 is the maximum quality.
Then the quality as the number increases the
quality get worse. So quality 1 is better than
quality 2, quality 2 better than quality 3,
and so on. Since I have RTX 5090, I am going
to use 32 GB VRAM configuration. However,
you will see that there are 2 versions: 32
GB of FP8 scaled and no FP8 scaled. The FP8
scaled has a big advantage. It is usually faster
because it uses lesser VRAM. Moreover, it uses
much lesser RAM memory. So if your RAM memory is
limited, then always go with FP8 scaled version.
So let's open nvitop to see our GPU and RAM
memory. pip install nvitop. nvitop. And this is
my current usages. So I have 60 GB of empty RAM
memory. My first GPU is fully empty. Therefore,
I will pick the very best configuration inside
Wan 2.2 trainings. Wan 2.2 text to image 32 GB.
And it is loaded. You can also click this icon
to be sure it is loaded. Then it is same as in
our Qwen image training tutorial. What I am
going to change here is the training dataset.
For text to image training, you only need to use
the images. For text to video training, if you
only use images, it is still working perfect as
I have shown in the beginning of the tutorial.
But you can also include videos. I will show
that later. So I will pick my training dataset,
but first let's prepare it. This is exactly same
logic as in the Qwen images, so this is my folder.
I will delete the other files to show you what
happens as a quick rewinding. But watch the Qwen
image training tutorial. So this is my trigger
word ohwx and this is my parent path. Don't worry,
it will automatically resize them. So this is
it. I copy pasted, I can also pick from here.
The best working resolution is 960 to 960.
How do I know? I have literally tested so
many different configurations. So when you
see these configurations 1024, 1280, 1328,
these are the resolutions that I have tested.
And the best yielding resolution is 960 to 960.
Therefore, I recommend that. Then don't forget
to click generate dataset configuration and
it is ready. So when you return back to your
images folder, you should see the txt files.
These are the captions and when you open
one of them you will see only the folder
name is used. If you want to use custom
captions, you need to change these files.
Okay, our training dataset is ready. Now we need
to set our output and other stuff same as in the
Qwen image training tutorial. So I will save
them into my test trainings folder like this
where the models will be saved. This is the model
LoRA models file names. Currently fine tuning is
not supported so we can only train LoRA. Okay,
then the model settings. You need to pick the
files for text to image training, we are only use
the low noise. There are 2 versions of Wan 2.2:
high noise and low noise. High noise is the
initial generation which roughly generates
the base of the image or video. The low noise
is the details. For generating only images,
we are only using low noise. This is the higher
quality. So I will pick the accurate models from
downloaded models training models Wan. So
this is the low noise text to video model.
Like this. Then since other files are there, I
will just copy paste the folder paths like this,
like this. But you can individually pick them.
We are not going to use Clip Vision, this is not
used for Wan 2.2 training. And you see there is
high noise. This is used for dual model training
which I will explain after this. So you don't need
to change anything else here. Don't change them.
In the training settings, you need to set your
training epochs as I have explained. Since I
have 28 images, I am going to use 200 epochs. If
you have 100 images, then you can reduce this to
100. That is the logic. But up to 50 images, I
recommend to train at least 200 epochs. Moreover,
there is save every N epochs. So we are saving
every 20 epochs. It will save 10 checkpoints that
I can compare later. Then don't forget to save
your configuration. So let's save this as like
this. LoRA tutorial text to image TOML. Okay, I
will save it. Then I will click start training.
Then follow the CMD window. If you get
any errors, you need to report me that.
So currently I have an error. Let's see where we
have the error. Maybe we forgot something. Yes,
I have forgotten the VAE path. This can happen.
So let's open all the panels like this and
search for VAE. Okay, the VAE is set here.
Okay, I can see the error that I have made,
so I need to fix it. It will be like this. And
this is also error. Okay, it will be like this.
So pay attention to the model paths save. You can
use the folder icon start training. And you see
we are also supporting torch compile. I am using
your Visual Studio installation automatically.
Therefore, it is super important for you to
follow the requirements tutorial which you
must. So the requirements tutorial are listed
here in the post. Follow this requirements
tutorial first. When you follow the Qwen image
models training, you will know this already.
Okay, let's follow our training. So now
it is loading model into the RAM memory,
then it will load into the GPU memory. If you
don't have sufficient amount of RAM memory,
training both models, both low and high noise,
is harder. And it is even not mandatory. You can
also train only low noise model and even generate
videos. It will be a little bit lower quality,
but it will work. Don't worry. So the training
is about to start. Yes, training starting. Okay,
training started. It is not using my entire GPU
memory. This is good. You need to have some free
memory. You will also see that your VRAM usage
is not static like this. This is because how
Kohya developed the Wan 2.2 model training. It
clears the VRAM cache after every step because
it is designed to be work with both models at
the same time during training. So the speed
is around 5 seconds per IT. It will get a little
bit slower. This is how Kohya displays currently.
But it is pretty decent. It is taking like 8
hours on my GPU. If I need faster training,
then I can reduce the resolution or I can increase
the learning rate and I can do lesser epoch. So
let's say you want 100 epochs, then you need to
multiply your learning rate with 2.5 and reduce
the maximum epochs number. However, you will
lose some quality. So this set learning rate
and number of epochs are the best overall. It is
a choice. It is a trade off. Either you need to
reduce the resolution to speed up or you need to
lower the epoch count and increase your learning
rate. So this will train text to image LoRAs for
us which you can use for text to video as well.
How we are going to use the trained models?
I will stop the training. So for using the
trained models, we are going to use SwarmUI. The
SwarmUI link is here. So let's also proceed with
it. If you don't know how to use SwarmUI
already, you need to follow this tutorial.
You see this is the tutorial link in
the top of the post. When you open it,
copy the zip file there. So let's download the
latest zip file from here. Then I will move it
into my existing SwarmUI installation like this.
Copy the file there. Right click and extract files
here and overwrite all. Then as a next step, we
will update our ComfyUI installation. So go to
ComfyUI link from here. Download the latest
zip file. You see there are 2 versions with
password protected one. If your antivirus, this
happens with Windows Defender, causes issues,
download with the password protected, then move
your ComfyUI zip file into your folder or you can
make a fresh installation. As usual, make an file
extraction overwrite all files. Then to update or
install Windows install or update comfyui.bat
file. We have moved the installation to uv
packages. So now it is much faster than before.
Both update and installation. So you see it is
all updated. Then return back to your SwarmUI. In
the SwarmUI, we have Windows update swarmui. So
double click it run. It will update SwarmUI and
start your application. Everything was already
explained in other tutorials in more details,
so you should watch them. Okay, SwarmUI update
succeed and it started. You will also get this
error. This is not important, just ignore that.
First of all, you need to get the latest presets.
So you can use import, choose file, go back to
your SwarmUI installation and select the latest
preset from here. Then overwrite existing presets.
Alternatively, while the application is running,
you can use the preset delete import. This will
delete your existing presets and just refresh it.
Then click refresh and everything is here. The
presets are important because I have updated the
presets for video generation for Wan 2.2 and also
image generation. So use the latest presets. Now
how we are going to use our trained Wan 2.2 image
generation LoRAs. So first of all, quick tools
reset params to default. Then from the presets,
the preset that you need to use is Wan 2.2
generate realistic images. Click here and
direct apply. This will let you generate 960
to 960 images. So let's type our prompt. Select
your aspect ratio whichever you want. For example,
this one. And then you need to select your LoRA.
But there is one more thing. You need to have
models downloaded for this preset to work. So
how you are going to download accurate models?
You see Windows start download models app.bat
file. This will start the model downloader
latest version. We have upgraded this. Also
it is using uv package. So now it is even faster
to start. Okay, the downloader started. So which
models you need to download? You can download
complete image generation and editing bundle.
Or you can download Wan 2.2 core 4 steps
bundle. This is my recommended bundle. So
go to bottom and download all models inside
this bundle. This way you will have all the
models that you need. Even the upscaler models
that you need to use to get maximum quality.
You can follow the download process from the
CMD window. So if I am missing any models,
they will get downloaded. If I already have some
models, they will be verified and it will skip
the download. So currently it is downloading
some of my missing models, but I have the
necessary models for image generation which is
Wan 2.2 text to video low noise. So it is set.
Now I need to set my LoRA. So these are the LoRAs
that it finds. It is compatible with Wan 2.2. My
trained LoRA is inside here. Wan 2.2 low noise.
This is my trained LoRA. This is 200 epochs
training results. As in the Qwen image training
tutorial, you should compare your checkpoints
with grid system and verify which model,
which checkpoint is the best. Like 20 epochs,
40 epochs, 60, 80. So this is 200 epochs. And
let's generate 4 random images. Currently this
is using our ComfyUI installation. It
was updated. It is using Sage Attention,
my first GPU. Everything was previously
explained in other tutorials. Moreover,
you should follow your VRAM usage from nvitop
to see what is happening. I have the sufficient
amount of RAM memory and VRAM. If your GPU
is weak like 6 GB GPU, don't worry. Since
we are using the ComfyUI, it is automatically
doing block swapping and also CPU offloading,
RAM offloading. Therefore, no matter what GPU
you have, it will work. This is the beauty of
the SwarmUI with ComfyUI backend. So it is
doing all the optimizations that you need.
The image generation in the base resolution will
be pretty fast as you are seeing right now. Okay,
this was the first image. The face is not that
great. We should do either face inpainting or
we are going to do upscaling which I will show
in a moment. However, this took only 45 seconds.
You can also reduce the number of steps if you
want. But this model is not a small model. This
is a big model. 14 billion parameters. This
model is much more powerful than the Z Image
turbo model if you ask my opinion. Okay, this is
another image. So generate few images like this.
Okay. Let's say I liked this image. So I will
click reuse parameters. It will set its seed.
Then I will go to presets and I will apply the our
upscale. You see there is 2x upscale direct apply.
And I will regenerate. Let's see the difference.
Furthermore, you can change the base resolution
of this model. Up to 1280 to 1280. 1280 to 1280.
This model is able to generate images. Sometimes
it may add some hallucinations to the right and
left border. But you can increase the resolution,
the base resolution to 1280 to 1280. I will
show after this how to do that. But let's
see the upscaled result. So as a reminding, let
me remind you where you put your trained LoRAs.
They are put inside SwarmUI inside models inside
LoRA folder. This is where you need to put your
trained LoRAs. Inside LoRA folder. Okay, now
it is upscaling. The upscaling will take more
time obviously because we are doubling the image
resolution. So as I said, don't worry if you don't
have a powerful GPU, it will still work with
automatic block swapping and CPU offloading.
Everything will be handled by the ComfyUI.
No matter what GPU you have, it will work.
And here it is. So let's make a comparison.
This was the base image. You see this was the
base image. Then this is the upscaled image.
As you can see, it fixed the face. It added
huge amount of details, quality. There is a
significant difference between the base image
and the generated upscaled image. Again, as I
said, you can increase the base resolution even
up to actually 1920 to 1080. However, it may add
some hallucinations. Let's try this and to see
the difference. But in my experimentation what I
did was I selected my model which is low noise.
So here low noise. So click this hamburger menu,
edit metadata, and change this to 1280 1280. Okay,
like this. Save. Then select another model and
select your model. It will update resolutions
accordingly. So when you select your aspect ratio
now, it will set it accordingly to 1280 to 1280
base resolution. These are all optional. You can
do whichever you want. And generate another image
with 1280 to 1280 total resolution. The aspect
ratio is like this. But let's see also 1920 to
1080 result as well. Okay. Yeah, not bad.
Not as good as upscale but not bad at all.
Now with this 1280 to 1280 base resolution, if I
also do upscale which I did in the example images,
it will become much better. For example, let
me show you from the history row and Wan 2.2.
I have shown in the beginning of the tutorial but
let's see again. So you see these images are huge,
massive. If I open, this is 3360 to 1920 pixels.
Therefore, it has huge amount of details. I mean
look at these details. So you can generate
massive images as well with this strategy.
Set the base resolution and upscale. Okay, this
is 1280 to 1280. Now I will reuse parameters
and enable my upscale preset one more time. It
is here direct apply and generate. Now it will
upscale this image into twice resolution.
Of course, it will take time. However,
it will be the maximum quality. So this image
full HD was generated in 73 seconds. This image
1280 to 1280 was generated in 55 seconds. This
big image was generated in 2 minute 25 seconds.
I mean these are the expected times because
we are generating really high quality images,
really high resolution images with perfect
accuracy. And this is literally the first
generation that we did. So I can generate
more and pick the better ones and as you
do more generations you will understand
how the model works, what are the basics.
Okay, so the upscale of the 1280 to 1280
completed and let's look at the difference
one more time. So this is upscaled and
this was the base. So from this base,
we upscaled into this masterpiece. The
resolution is just amazing. The details,
the realism, everything is mind blowing compared
to the other models. So can you use this model,
this only images trained low noise model
for video generation? Yes. It will be
a little bit lower quality, but yes. Let me
demonstrate that. So I will copy this prompt.
You can also use this for image to video as well,
don't worry. Everything is same. So let's refresh.
Reset params to default. And there are several
options that you can use. For the highest quality,
you need to use Wan 2.2 high quality text to video
20 steps. This will take some time. On my GPU it
takes like 6 to 7 minutes. Or you can use the
lightning LoRA based one. You see Wan 2.2 text to
video. So let's see the lightning LoRA first, then
let's see the other one. Then let's proceed to
dual model training. So direct apply. You see it
is going to set the low and high noise LoRAs like
this automatically for you. Copy paste your prompt
and select your trained LoRA. So this was the low
noise LoRA. Then generate. This will be pretty
fast because it is only total 4 steps. And again,
for this preset to work flawlessly, you need to
download this bundle. Or you will be having issues
with the models finding them, setting them.
I am doing everything automatically for you.
Okay, so the generation started. First it is
starting to use the high noise Wan 2.2 model.
Then it will use the low noise model. However,
we should change the prompt to into a video
of. So it will be a little bit better. When you
switch presets like this, since your base model
will change, it will take some time for loading
reloading models, but everything is automatically
and properly made by the ComfyUI. So you shouldn't
have any problems. And as you can see, it is able
to 100 percentage utilize my GPU. It is using
my GPU 575 watts at once. So it is maximum power
usage. Okay, it is starting to generate. Since
we trained our LoRA only on low noise model, this
will work a little bit lower quality than training
on dual models which I will show. However,
you can use this LoRA on image to video presets
as well. I will show that too after this. Okay,
so the video has been generated. Let's see
the video. Yes, I can see the resemblance
and accuracy. It is pretty good as you can
see. This is base video. If I upscale it,
it would be better, but I can certainly see the
resemblance especially as it gets closer. Let me
show you the final frame perhaps like this. And
it only took how many minutes. It only took 111
seconds. So it takes lesser than 2 minutes. If I
want better quality, then I need to switch to this
preset. This will do real 20 steps with real
CFG scale and it will be much higher quality.
What about using this on image to video. Can I do
that? Yes. So I will do reset params to default.
Go to presets. With image to video again we have 2
quality presets. You can use this high quality or
you can use Wan 2.2 image to video 4 steps. This
is also really good quality. So direct apply. Then
let's select our prompt like this. I don't need
to copy this of course this time. Just copy paste
the prompt. Then as an image for example let's use
this image. So I will go to init image choose file
then choose this then resolution close use closest
aspect ratio. And the preset was not selected.
Yes, I need to select the preset so refresh. Reset
params to default. Then refresh models to be sure
you have everything. Then presets and let's go
to presets. Okay this one direct apply. Yes,
you see it has selected the accurate model. This
is important apply. Then let's go to init image
choose file select our photo closest aspect ratio.
Okay. Now I also need to select my LoRA. So my
LoRA was let's see this one. This is only trained
with the images on low noise and generate. This is
also 4 steps. So therefore it will be pretty good.
However, since we are switching a lot of models,
it may leave some left over. Therefore what
I am going to do is I will cancel this first.
Then server backend and restart all backends.
This will refresh my memory usages like this.
You see it cleared everything. If you are going to
do a lot of model switching, you can restart your
backend to clear your VRAM and RAM memory and then
generate. Now it should work better. Otherwise you
need to trust the ComfyUI RAM management. So I
recommend to restart backends when you are going
to do big models switching like this. Because
we switched from LoRA text to video to image
to video. Okay, it is nice. It is loading into RAM
then starting generation. This should be also take
lesser than 2 minutes especially the second and
third generations. By the way this was an image
prompt. Therefore for video prompting you need
to do better. But I am just showing an example.
So this prompt is not made for video generation.
This was made for image generation. Therefore it
may not be perfect for video generation. However
still we should see the you know the quality and
video. I have tested that training text to
video model LoRA improves image to video as
well. Training image to video LoRA doesn't improve
that well. It is weird I know. Maybe it is because
I have trained with only images static images
not with videos. But this is really improving
image to video as well. So you can train an image
LoRA from text to video model with just images and
it will improve your image to video generations
as well. Okay, it failed for some reason maybe.
Let's see the logs. No I don't see any error.
Why it is showing an error. Okay, I think I
was out of RAM memory so the ComfyUI crashed
probably because I am already using 2 GPUs.
RAM memory on my computer with all other stuff
that is open. Okay, it crashed again due to out of
RAM memory. Therefore, I have added this argument:
--cache-none. When you add this into your backend,
it will cache none of the models. So this is
really useful when you are working with Wan 2.2
low and high noise models together at the same
time if you don't have sufficient amount of RAM
memory, especially system RAM memory. So this
way, it will use a model, generate, it will
then offload it, completely deleted, and load the
next model. This will minimize your RAM usage,
also VRAM usage, with delay of loading models
from the disk. But since my disks are fast,
it is not an issue. So it fixed the
issue. There is no more RAM leakage
or RAM accumulation and we are about to
get the video ready. It is pretty fast.
Okay, we got the video. So this was from image
to video. As we get, you know, distant from the
camera, the resemblance gets decreased, but
this was only static images trained model,
not the auto model. However, it is decent
and it took only 2.4 minutes generation. So,
how we are going to train on dual models?
Not only with the single model. If you want
to generate videos, this is what you should do.
So I will just disable my backend to minimize my
VRAM usage. Then go back to your SECourses
Musubi Tuner. So for dual model training,
we are just going to change our preset. So I will
open a new tab here. Go to 1 Models Training,
open folder. Go back to Wan 2.2 training
configurations. So we are going to use
text to video configs. These configurations train
both high noise and low noise models at the same
time. However, this will use more VRAM and this
will use more RAM memory since you need to have
both of the models loaded into your RAM memory.
Therefore, be careful. I recommend to begin with
fp8 scaled versions. Then once you verified it
is working, you can move to non-fp8. So let's
begin with fp8 scaled. Again, always save your
configurations like this. Then we need to set
the output directory. Don't forget that. So
I can just copy paste the directories here.
Training dataset. Again, I am only using static
images. If you use videos, the videos will use
more VRAM memory. Therefore, be very careful.
If you use videos, then you need to have more
VRAM memory, RAM memory. You need to do more
block swapping. You may need to reduce your
training resolution. Everything changes. So first,
train with only static images, verify results,
get some results, get some test done, then you can
include videos into your training dataset. You can
have multiple subfolders for different training
datasets and for each dataset have different
resolutions. So let me demonstrate an example.
So what I did is I generated another folder like
this, 1_ohwx_video. However, I will be needed
to set different captions, not automatic ones.
So I will copy paste it here. As I said, first I
recommend to train with only static images then
include videos. But I will show how to include
videos. And generate dataset configuration. Now,
it will generate datasets like this. You need to
edit this TOML file. Why? Because you will see
that it is using the same resolution for both
images and videos. What does this mean? This
means that if your images are high resolution,
the videos will be too high resolution. Either
you need to auto downscale your videos to lower
resolution or you need to edit this TOML file.
So I will open this TOML file. It is saved
inside this folder. You need to do this manually.
So this is the generated TOML file. You can see
that there are 2 different datasets. The first
one is the image dataset and the second one is
the video dataset. And in the video dataset,
it is going to use some frame extraction method
and it is going to use some methods like frame
extraction head, target frames, number of repeats,
max frames. So I am going to set resolution here
as well and change the resolution like 480 to
480. So that it will use this resolution for
this dataset. You can also change the resolution
of the image dataset from here. So you can have
different dataset resolutions. And if you are
wondering what are these other options for
video datasets, it is all written here with
details. When you scroll down, you will see
dataset preparation details. Open this and read
here. However, as I said multiple times now,
train with only images then verify your results
then do training with video dataset. Moreover,
now since we have 2 different folders, you will
see that it generated the captions like this
for the video dataset. So you need to change the
caption of the video as well. I didn't test this.
Probably this will work best with just trigger
word or you can describe the video action as
well in these captions. However, for using the
static images, I recommend only trigger word
as a caption. So I will delete this and I will
regenerate dataset configuration. Yes. Now it will
use only my images dataset. It shows 56 double
times but it is okay. There is actually 28 images.
Okay, we did set the dataset. This is
how you prepare your video training
datasets. Then we set the other things same
as the previous training. So in the models,
I will just copy paste the paths here, here,
here. And additionally, for this model,
you need to set the high noise model as well. So
it is here. So I will set it like this. You see,
high noise. And that's it. Now I will save my
configuration and click training. It should
start and work right away. However, you need
to have more RAM memory for this to work and it
will use a little bit more VRAM memory as well.
So let's see what happens. The training window
is here. You will see that it will load both low
noise and high noise models into the your system.
You should see them in the CMD window. So first
it is loading the low noise then it is loading
the high noise. Low noise is for details,
high noise is for the initial generation,
the base structure. We train only low noise for
image generation. However, if you want to generate
videos, you should train on both of them. You can
also train them individually one by one. However,
its quality is lower than training this dual
model configuration. So you can load the image
configuration, image training configuration,
change low noise model to high noise model. It
will work exactly same and train high noise
model. If your system is not able to train
both models at the same time, you can follow
that strategy. But what I recommend is rent
a machine from the RunPod or Massed Compute
which I will show and train there and use.
Okay, it started. As you can see, both of the
models is running at the same time now. You will
see that it will fluctuate the VRAM usage and how
it changes model is like 87 percent. Okay, you see
the RAM usage increased because now it is loading
the other model and it is switching between them.
Okay, you see. It is working nice. It is using
almost my entire RAM memory right now so I should
decrease my RAM memory usage. I can also reduce my
block swap count because I still have some VRAM.
So where you increase or decrease the block swap?
So let's open all panels, search for swap and
you will see that there is block swap. So you can
change block swaps. Currently since it is fitting
into my VRAM entirely with fp8 scaled, I am not
doing any block swap. But if it doesn't fit in
your case, you need to increase this like 10, 20,
15. Moreover, I can use offload inactive DiT to
CPU. This requires more RAM memory and it is not
compatible with blocks to swap. So when you do
block swap, you cannot use this unfortunately.
Therefore, it is the fastest training that I
can get right now. Its speed is very good as
you can see. It is also faster than training
only image model right now because I am doing fp8
scaled training. If I were doing not fp8 scaling,
I would be needed to do block swapping and block
swapping reduces your speed. So this dual model
training takes like 6 hours on my GPU, maybe
even faster. This is how you train dual model.
And how you use dual model? Exactly same as the
single image training. I only change my LoRA to
use it. So let's enable back our backend and let's
open a new tab. Copy our prompt. Quick tools,
reset params to default presets. And let's use
this high quality preset this time. Direct apply.
Type our prompt like this. Okay. Make sure to
not include the LoRAs in your prompt when you
copy paste. Okay, it is like this. And I need to
select my LoRA. So my LoRA is this one. High noise
low noise auto. So this was trained exactly as I
have just shown you. This is the highest quality
and let's generate. So this generation will
take significantly more time compared to the
fast generation which is Wan 2.2 text to video 8
steps. Actually this is 4 steps. I forgotten to
change its name. Yes, this is 4 steps. So it will
take more time but this is the highest quality
that you are going to get with video generation,
with text to video generation. For image to video,
it doesn't make that much big difference. You can
perfectly use this preset. But for text to video
generation, it makes really big difference
still because none of the recent LoRAs are,
the lightning LoRAs are still as good as the image
to video LoRAs. I am using the latest LoRA which
was published only 3 days ago. You see they
are 17 December 2025 LoRAs but it is as I say.
So the generation started. As you can see, it
should be done in like 6 minutes if I remember
correctly. We will see. Okay, so we got our video
generated. It is not the best video. The quality
is good but the prompt is bad. So therefore I
need to edit my prompt and generate new one.
The prompting do matters a lot. So play with your
prompts to get the best results. Remember all the
generations will be inside your SwarmUI, inside
output, inside local, inside raw folder. So you
will see all of your generations here. They will
be saved by the date, latest date folder. You will
see and find your images and videos in this
folder if you need them later. Furthermore,
you will see them in the history tab as well
from the raw and with the folders like this.
So as a next step, I will show how to train on
Massed Compute then I will show on RunPod. So
for Massed Compute, enter inside the extracted zip
file folder and open Massed Compute instructions
read txt. Reading this file is mandatory
and watching the Windows tutorial part are
mandatory. Please use this link to register. I
appreciate that very much. Then go to billing
and set up some credits. They accept crypto
payments as well. Then go to deploy. In here,
I recommend you to use RTX Pro 6000 Blackwell GPU.
This is working really great. From the category,
select creator, select SECourses. Then enter
your coupon. This is important. We are going
to use Category Creator, Image SECourses
and discount coupon SECourses. You see the,
this very powerful GPU is 1.8 dollars
per hour. When I apply my coupon,
it becomes 1.35 dollars. If you want
even more powerful GPU, faster training,
select H200 NVL. This is even more powerful than
RTX Pro 6000. It is 2.6 dollars. With our coupon,
it becomes 1.95 dollars. This is the fastest GPU.
So you can use either of them. Let's use H200 for
this demonstration, for this tutorial. Deploy.
Now we need to wait for machine to initialize.
To connect our machine, we are going to
use ThinLinc Client. Download it. If you
followed other tutorials, you already know. After
downloading, just next, next, next. Then you need
to set your shared folder from local devices.
You see clipboard synchronization and drives.
And in here I have a shared folder with read
and write permission. So I can copy my small
files and I can connect. For big files, you
need to watch this tutorial. This will show
you how to upload and download big files to
Hugging Face. You can also use Google Drive
or OneDrive. So other cloud services as well. You
know how to use them. But you cannot use ThinLinc
Client to transfer big files. So let's just
wait for initialization to be complete. Okay,
now it is running. You may refresh page time to
time to update but it was auto updated for me.
Then click here and copy login URL. Open ThinLinc
Client. Copy username for first time users and
copy password and connect. Then continue. Then
click start. It will start the machine and
connect from the ThinLinc Client. Remember this
is running on a remote machine, not on my machine.
Now I need to transfer my file, my installer file.
You can use Patreon login from this browser or you
can use the shared folder which I prefer. So I
will copy my file into my shared folder. You can
also put your training images here. Go back to
home from here. Go to Thin Drives. This is your
shared folder. Do not run anything inside here.
Run everything from downloads folder. Whatever it
is. It doesn't matter. The transfer speeds are not
great with ThinLinc Client. Therefore you should
use the other method that I have just shown you,
the link. You see this link for big files. Okay,
I will copy paste my images. Drag and drop or copy
paste both works. And our latest SECourses Musubi
Tuner Premium Installer. So it is here. Drag and
drop into downloads folder. Wait for files to be
transferred. You see it is being transferred right
now. Then go to downloads folder. Extract the
Musubi Tuner. Extract here. And I will open the
Massed Compute instructions. Copy this command.
While I am inside this folder, open in terminal.
This is important. And paste. You need to be
in the accurate folder. Then it will start the
installation. You will see that installation is
lightning fast. Actually let's see in real time.
So it is going to use uv package installation.
I mean look at the speed. Look at the
installation speed. It will take like
30 seconds. Maybe 1 minute maximum. So it is
almost done. Also we need to download training
models. So in here you see there is this command.
python3 download_train_models. Again while I am
inside this folder, open in terminal. Paste. And
it will ask you which models to download. So let's
download text to video option 4. The download will
begin. The downloader is also optimized. It will
be pretty fast. You see 500 megabytes per second.
So it is 4 gigabits per second. 4 gigabits. So it
will be done almost in no time. The installation
also completed and the trainer started. You see
installation take like 60 seconds. The rest
is exactly same as in the Windows tutorial.
You will open your configuration. And there
is one advantage because configuration is
set for Massed Compute folders directly. So
I will download the Wan 2.2 training configs,
text to video configs. Whether you want to
use dual GPU or whichever GPU. So this one
is using 140 gigabytes of GPU. Let's see our
VRAM. nvidia-smi. Okay we have 140 gigabytes.
Therefore I am going to use this config. I
hope it fits. You see it is maximum. Then
I need to set my output folder and other thing.
I think output folder is already set. So I need
to set my training images or videos. So
extract here. Okay. So copy this path and
copy paste here. Then don't forget to click
generate dataset configuration. And let's see
if the model download is completed. Yes almost
completed. You see 3 over 4. It is verifying.
So literally with like 5 minutes setup, you
can begin training in Massed Compute. Like 5
minutes. Maybe 4 minutes. Once you do this like 1
or 2 times, you will get used to it. You will be
immediately setup a machine and start training
right away. Okay high noise model is getting
verified. I am also verifying files. Therefore
you will never have any issues with downloaded
models. This is super important because sometimes
models get corrupted and it is causing a lot of
issues. Okay it is downloading the last model.
It is 50 seconds remaining time. Okay so all
the downloads have been completed. Now I did
set the training dataset and start training.
It should work if the folder paths are accurate
if I remember but probably we need to change one
more thing. Not ready yet. So in the 1 Models
Settings, yes. You see this is 23 version so I
need to make this 24. You also need to change
that. The output folder should be okay. Yes
it is okay. And start training. Now let's see.
Oh by the way if this was a 2 model training,
yes it was. I need to also change this. So
dual model. Okay. Now it will give another
error and I will click training again. So first
it is caching the training dataset. Okay it
is loading. Okay I will stop and click start
again. Yes now it should work perfectly fine.
Let's follow both of that. So let's zoom in.
Another zoom. Okay. Let's see in real time. So
starting training. Loading models. You see loading
models are amazingly fast. Blazing fast on Massed
Compute. This is why I like Massed Compute over
RunPod. The disk speed on Massed Compute is like
10x, maybe 20x faster than the RunPod. Okay 77
gigabytes. Okay now it is training the low noise
then it will begin the high noise. Okay training
is starting. 4 steps done on the first model then
it will load the second model. The logic of dual
training is that it switches models between. Okay
why it is taking time? I think the first step is
taking time. Okay. Now it did begin. Yes. So the
training started. We will see the training speed
gets better. Okay it is using 80 gigabytes right
now. But the training speed is getting better.
You see 2.2 second. It will get faster than 1 IT
per second. But it is still switching models.
So what we can do, we can disable this and
see if it works. So let's disable this to get
even faster. Did we load the inaccurate model?
Yeah this should be disabled. I will update
this configuration for you so you won't have
this issue. Now it should be even faster than
before because it will not offload each model.
It will load both of the models into the GPU.
Let's see the speed. Of course you can enable
fp8 scaled. It will take even lesser VRAM so you
can load it into like 80 gigabytes GPUs as well.
Okay training started. You see it is 1.5
IT per second using only 106 gigabytes of
GPU. I will update the configuration so
you won't have this issue. But this is
the training speed. It is going to
take only 67 minutes. So with like
2 dollars, you will be able to train very best
Wan 2.2 model. And it's a dual model training,
not single model. You are seeing the speed right
now. 1.35 IT per second. It is amazing. And it
will take only 68 minutes and we are doing 5600
steps. Not a low number of steps. So it is working
just amazing. Yes I have updated the config as
140 gigabytes and it is using 107 gigabytes GPU.
So now I will show how to train on RunPod. The
rest of the Massed Compute is same. You just
need to download your LoRA files and use
on your computer or you can use in Massed
Compute as well. If you wonder how to use
on Massed Compute, on our channel SECourses,
we have a video for this. The video is this one.
Generate AI art 10x faster. The ultimate SwarmUI
and ComfyUI cloud tutorial. You can watch this
tutorial to learn how to use SwarmUI on Massed
Compute or on RunPod. This tutorial covers both
of them. So for training on RunPod, we have RunPod
instructions. Open that file. Always you need
to follow this file for RunPod. Please register
RunPod from this link. After registering and
logging in, go to billing and set up some credits.
Then once you have the credits, go to pods.
If you want to use permanent storage, I have
a tutorial for that. It is here. If you want
to learn how to upload and download big files,
the tutorial is here. And if you want to learn
RunPod usage, there is another tutorial here.
So I will show on RunPod with RTX 5090. One of
the most commonly used one. But you can use bigger
GPUs like B200 for even faster training. So this
is the disk type and this is the RAM GPU filters
that I use. Let's select RTX 5090. Now a lot of
people are getting confused here. You are not
going to use this template. You are always going
to use the template that I write in this file.
Always. Because my installers are optimized for
whatever it is written here. Otherwise you will
get errors. So change template. Select PyTorch
2.2.0. This is official template. Click edit
and increase the disk size like 200. It is up to
you. If you want to save more checkpoints, you
need to increase this. Set overrides and deploy on
demand. Now we need to wait for machine to become
ready but it should be very fast because this
is official template. This is very lightweight
template. So let's see. Time to time click here.
Okay it is ready. Jupyter Lab. If this doesn't
open, you need to refresh, click some several
times. If still doesn't work, get a new machine.
Then I will upload my downloaded zip file. Wait
for upload to complete. You see in the bottom it
shows. Then right click and extract archive.
Click refresh. Then open RunPod instructions
read txt file. Copy this command. Open a new
terminal from here. And terminal. Make sure
that you are in the workspace and copy paste
like this. Then it will start the installation.
So run the commands inside workspace folder.
Open new terminal. Make sure that you are in the
workspace wherever you have extracted the files.
The installation will be extremely fast compared
to before. Why? Because we are using uv package.
While installation is continuing, let's download
the model because model download may be slow.
Open another terminal. Copy paste. Select the
model text to video. It will start downloading.
This is also super optimized. Let's see. You
see it is downloading with like 300 megabytes per
second. Pretty good. The uv installation is also
ultra fast. Before it was taking sometimes 10
minutes, 20 minutes, 30 minutes to install. Now
it will take only few minutes to install. This
is our latest optimization. I will move my all
installers to uv installation hopefully slowly.
So you will always install my applications much
faster now compared to before. Also models
are getting downloading meanwhile. So after
installation it will auto start the application.
This warning is not important. You will get
this in all installers. The model merging and
verification on RunPod is sadly slow compared
to Massed Compute because its disk speed
is very slow compared to Massed Compute.
Okay application installation completed and
started. I will open the Gradio live link.
However model downloading is still continuing.
Meanwhile let's also upload our training images.
So for upload click this icon. Select your
training images as a zip file. Upload. I
prefer this way of uploading. So we can set up the
configuration while models are getting downloaded.
Wait for upload to be completed. You see it is
slow. You can also use runpodctl for uploading.
I explain that in another tutorial video. For
example you can watch this one. But it is not
mandatory to learn or you can use this tutorial
to upload and download big files very fast. This
is the recommended tutorial. And interface
is here. This is running on RunPod. 1 Models
Training. So from the configurations, let's
pick the configuration we want to use. Let's
use the text to image configuration. So you see
we have 32 gigabytes. Copy path. Right click and
copy path. Put a backslash. Always RunPod
puts a backslash to beginning of path and
paste it. Then click this. It will auto load the
config. You see it is loaded successfully. Then
set your output folder. Let's save them inside
workspace a new folder: Trained LoRAs. Right
click and copy path. Then paste it here. Put a
backslash to the beginning. This is important.
If you want to do Qwen training, it is same. We
only load Qwen training into here. So this is how
you train on RunPod. You can change your save
name or save every n epochs. And the training
dataset. So I have uploaded my images. Right click
and extract archive. And they are named like this.
Remember this is mandatory. 1_ohwx. ohwx will be
our captions. 1 is the repeating. So I am going to
give the path of the parent folder. Copy as, right
click and copy as path. Backslash, put the path
then click generate dataset configuration.
It is done. Then the 1 Models Settings,
we need to set the folder paths. So the models are
downloaded inside Training Models 1. So copy path
and change them like this. And backslash. Okay.
No not like this. It needs to be like this. Yes.
So this is the accurate pathing on RunPod. So like
this. Yes. Verify the paths. And like this. Okay
all paths are set. This is single model so there
is no high noise. And what else is left? Nothing
else is left. Save your configuration always.
So you can load later if any error happens,
if you restart. Okay the models are still being
downloaded. We need to wait them to be completed.
If you use RunPod permanent network storage
system, you won't be needed to wait. However
currently we are not using. But it is also
very slow. I mean unbearably slow. And you
see only 260 megabyte per second disk speed. On
Massed Compute this is 2 gigabytes per second.
Okay all models downloaded. It is verifying the
last one. So we can start training. So make sure
to save and click start training. Then we will
follow what is happening on CMD window. This
is where we see the actual logs. If there is any
error, you need to report from here. Unfortunately
setting up RunPod, starting training is like
10x slower than the Massed Compute. But it has
some other advantages like permanent storage or
more GPU options. However this is the reality.
You see I click start training and I am still
waiting for it to read from the disk to start
caching, loading models. Okay let's also install
nvitop. pip install nvitop and just type nvitop.
So we can monitor the GPU usage as well. If
you don't see GPU here, that means that your
machine is broken. It is going to start caching
the text encoder outputs. It is started. Nice.
Now it will load model. Oh one more thing. We can
increase the model loading speed. So I will stop
training. How? Open all panels and search for
loading and disable numpy memory mapping. This
will increase your loading speed significantly
on RunPod. So start training. Don't worry it
will just resume from wherever it is left. So we
didn't lose any time. This is really speeding up
the model loadings on RunPod. Okay now we need
to wait again. Okay it is loading the model.
Pretty fast. This optimization is making huge
difference on RunPod. This has been implemented
after I have taught this issue to Kohya. But
still nothing fast as the Massed Compute.
Okay training starting. You can monitor the GPU
from nvitop. Yes started. You see the first step
speed was very slow. Now 1.46, 2 second IT, 2.15
second IT. This is slower than the other GPUs
because we are also doing some block swapping
since this is not fp8 scaled. So when we go
to swap, let's see how many we are doing. We are
doing 10 block swapping. If you want even faster
training, you can do fp8 scaled training and
you can make the block swap zero and it will be
faster. But this is okay speed. It is going to
take like 4 5 hours. So it is bearable maybe a
little bit more. But this is how you do training
on RunPod. The models will be saved inside my
Trained LoRAs folder. You see it is already
generated and the dataset TOML file is saved
there. The training TOML file also saved there
when you click training. So you will download
LoRAs from here and use them. Or if you want to
use them on RunPod, we have a tutorial for how
to use SwarmUI and ComfyUI on RunPod. It is here.
This is a very recent tutorial. Fully up to date.
So you can follow this tutorial to learn how
to use SwarmUI and ComfyUI on RunPod and Massed
Compute. So this is it. I hope you have enjoyed.
Don't forget to stop your machine, terminate your
machine. On Massed Compute, you need to delete
your machine. Stopping your machine will not
stop your credit spending. Don't forget that. But
before deleting, make sure to backup all of your
data. On RunPod, you can stop your machine and
it will keep your data then you need to terminate
your machine to completely avoid credit usage. But
stopping machine will make it very minimal amount
of credit usage. If you have any questions, always
ask me. We have Z Image Turbo LoRA training, very
up to date, working amazing, very lightweight.
We have Flux SRPO training updated. We have Qwen
training that you need to watch. Hopefully more
videos are coming, more applications are coming.
I am working 7 days every week literally like 10
hours a day. So stay subscribed, leave a comment,
ask questions, join our Discord, ask questions,
message me from Patreon. Hopefully see you later.